Have you ever wondered
if there are more natural ways
to lower your high blood pressure,
guard against Alzheimer's,
lose weight, and feel better?
Well, it turns out there is!
Welcome to the
Nutrition Facts Podcast.
I’m your host,
Dr. Michael Greger.
Today we wrap up our
series on the enzyme NAD+
and we start with a cautionary tale
about NAD-boosting supplements.
Most of the reported
side effects
for NAD+ precursors,
like NAM, NR, and NMN,
are relatively rare and minor,
for example, diarrhea,
nausea, rashes, hot flashes,
and leg cramps.
Both NR and NMN
raise NAM levels,
so may share
in the same concerns
regarding sirtuin inhibition,
methyl depletion,
and potential adverse effects
of NAM breakdown products.
Another theoretical concern
of NAD+ boosting
is the exacerbation
of infections
by a group of bacteria
called Haemophilus
(from the Greek
meaning "blood loving,"
though can also cause
infections of the lungs,
brain, throat,
flesh, and joints).
Haemophilus bacteria lack
the ability to make NAD+,
so rely on host levels,
raising the possibility
that higher blood levels
might worsen the disease course
of infected individuals.
Ironically,
elevated NAD+ levels
may also fuel
immune system overreaction
in cases of auto-immune
and inflammatory disease.
When fully activated,
the immune system is voracious.
The immune reaction
to a blood infection
or extensive burns can burn
4,000 calories a day,
approximating military training
in the Arctic.
Since NAD+ is used by cells
to produce energy,
it's no surprise that we find
the primary NAD+
synthesizing enzyme
strongly upregulated
in tissues
that are actively inflamed.
For example,
the enzyme NAMPT is elevated
in colonoscopy biopsies
taken from inflamed areas
in patients with
inflammatory bowel disease,
and higher levels
are correlated
with greater disease severity.
So, for those suffering from
chronic autoimmune diseases,
such as rheumatoid arthritis,
NAD+ boosting
could potentially have
a "profound negative impact."
This explains
why tamping down NAD+
with NAMPT inhibitors
has been shown
to ameliorate colitis
and arthritis in mice,
but this has yet
to be tested in people.
Such NAD+ depleting drugs
have, however,
been used in cancer patients.
Malignancy is another heavily
energy-consuming process.
NAD+ may, therefore,
have a tumor-promoting effect
by promoting cancer cell growth
and spread.
For example, NAMPT,
the NAD+-forming enzyme,
is highly expressed
in cancerous brain tumors
and correlates with
decreased patient survival.
This has led to attempts
to use NAD+-depleting therapies
to try to starve
cancer progression,
but this approach is confounded
by rapid onset injury
to another
energy-intensive tissue,
the retina,
risking blindness.
Giving NMN to mice
with pancreatic cancer
accelerates the progression
of the cancer,
thought due to the aggravation
of inflammation.
The researchers conclude that
consumers of NAD+ supplements
must "balance the advantageous
anti-ageing effects
with the potential detrimental
pro-tumorigenic side effects."
Perhaps this explains
why the best NAD+ boosters
have ever been able to do
is increase mice lifespan
by five percent.
On the other hand,
as you'll remember,
NAM successfully prevented
human skin cancers
and has been found
to reduce the incidence
of a variety
of carcinogen-induced tumors
in rodents.
The disparate results
may in part be due
to the disparate impact
sirtuin activation
may have on different cancers.
Sirtuin activity
can be overexpressed
in some cancers
(like thyroid carcinomas
and lung metastasis)
but reduced in others
(like brain, bladder, prostate,
and ovarian tumors).
The bottom line
is that particular caution
should be used
for NAD+-boosting supplements
by those with cancer,
or a personal or strong
family history of cancer,
and perhaps also by those
with inflammatory disorders
and certain active infections.
In our next story,
we look at how to naturally get
our bodies to make more NAD+
by boosting the NAD+-synthesizing
enzyme NAMPT.
So, which NAD+ boosting
supplement is best?
There’s no clear standout,
as hardly any of the preclinical
effects found in the lab
have translated into evidence
of human clinical benefit.
Perhaps, this failure is to be expected
given the complexity of NAD+ physiology,
with its juggling of multiple precursors,
production pathways, and recycling routes.
The bottom line is that it’s just too early
to say if NAD+ booster supplementation
will ever live up to even
a fraction of the hype.
Many more, larger, and longer-term studies
are necessary to establish safety and efficacy.
The problem is that because NA, NAM,
NR, and NMN are all natural products,
they can’t be patented;
so, the money for well-designed
clinical trials is not as available.
The reason there have been comparatively
more trials done on NR than NMN
is that patents were originally issued for NR
before being invalidated as unpatentable.
Perhaps blindly overloading the
system with NAD+ precursors
is not the best way to go
about NAD+ restoration.
The body seems too smart to allow such
blunt incursion to affect tissue levels.
Maybe these supplements are
just profit-making distractions
from more natural approaches.
Broadly, there are three main
ways to increase NAD+ levels.
Increasing the supply of NAD+
precursors is just the first.
The other two are having
the body make more,
by activating NAD+
synthesizing enzymes,
or have the body use less, via an
inhibition of excess NAD+ degradation.
The primary determinant of NAD+
synthesis in the enzyme NAMPT.
An abundance of NAMPT tends to
decrease with age in human muscle,
dropping steadily by about 40%
between the ages of 20 and 80.
In our liver, it drops by half.
However, age-related diseases,
such as atherosclerosis,
cancer, diabetes,
and rheumatoid arthritis,
have been found to exacerbate
NAMPT decline,
raising a chicken or
the egg question.
There’s where interventional
trials come in.
Similar NAMPT declines have been
noted in aging rats and mice.
Does boosting NAMPT help?
Increasing NAMPT or its species
equivalent increases the lifespans
of yeast, fruit flies, and rodents.
An NAMPT boost also increases aerobic
capacity and exercise endurance in mice,
in addition to helping them live longer.
Enhanced expression of NAMPT increases
the NAD+ levels in the muscles in mice
comparable to feeding them
dietary NAD+ precursors,
but if you remember,
NAD+ precursors don’t seem to be able to
affect NAD+ muscle levels in most people.
In fact, such supplements can
actually suppress NAMPT,
while boosting that methylating enzyme
to rid the body of the excess.
In addition to methyl depletion,
chronic administration
of these supplements
could potentially then leave people
worse off should they ever stop them.
There is, however, a way to naturally
boost NAMPT and NAD+ levels in humans
without any supplements: exercise.
Athletes have about twice the NAMPT
expression in their musculature
compared to sedentary individuals.
To prove cause and effect,
sedentary men and women started
a stationary bike exercise protocol,
and within three weeks, NAMPT
levels increased by 127%.
Resistance training can
also increase NAMPT,
and this can also translate into a
127% increase in muscle NAD+ levels
and a rise in sirtuin activity.
In other words,
exercise can do what NAD+
boosting supplements can’t.
Finally today,
how can we conserve NAD+
by preventing over-activation
of the enzymes PARP-1 and CD38,
which both guzzle down NAD+?
There are three
NAD+ boosting strategies:
Increasing the supply
of NAD+ precursors
is just one way.
The other two
are having the body make more,
by activating
NAD+-synthesizing enzymes,
or have the body use less,
by, for example,
conserving it, by using less.
Besides sirtuins,
the major consumers
of NAD+ are PARP-1 and CD38.
PARP-1 is an enzyme
that uses NAD+ to repair DNA.
The more oxidative DNA damage,
the more single
and double stranded DNA breaks,
the more enzymes like PARP-1
need to be activated
to come to the rescue.
This uses up a lot of NAD.
As DNA damage
accumulates with age,
the rising need
for repair enzymes like PARP-1
causes a major drain
on NAD+ levels.
Exposing cells in vitro
to DNA damaging agents,
such as gamma radiation
or genotoxic chemicals,
can cause an 80
to 90 percent drop
in NAD+ levels
within a matter of minutes.
This has led to the search
for PARP-1 blockers
to preserve NAD+ levels,
but rather than blocking
DNA repair,
why not work to prevent
so much damage
in the first place?
For example,
the severe oxidative stress
of a high-fat diet
can lead to PARP-1 activation
and NAD+ depletion in mice,
but NAD+ levels can be
"dramatically restored"
by feeding them
"purple sweet potato color,"
the natural
anthocyanin pigments
found in purple sweet potatoes.
Or, of course, you can just not
feed them a high-fat diet.
DNA repair is a good thing.
PARP-1 may be
one of the reasons
NAD+-boosting interventions
can improve healthspans
and lifespans
in laboratory animals.
Greater PARP activity
strongly correlates
with longer lifespan
across about a dozen
mammalian species,
and the PARP activity
of human centenarians
averages 60 percent higher
than younger controls.
However, persistent activation
can lead to NAD+ depletion,
and overactivation
can lead to cell death.
So, we should try to keep
oxidative stress to a minimum.
CD38 is another major guzzler
of NAD+.
It's an enzyme that uses NAD+
found concentrated
on the surfaces
of immune cells
and robustly induced
in the context of inflammation.
The rise of CD38 activity
with age
has been blamed on persistent
"inflammaging" activation,
the rise in systemic low-grade
inflammation in our bodies
when we get older,
which may be a major culprit
for falling NAD+ levels.
For example, blocking CD38
has been found
to raise NAD+ levels
in old mice
comparable to that
of younger mice.
So, oxidation and inflammation
can lead to a drop
in NAD+ levels,
due to the excess activation
of the NAD+ consuming enzymes.
This may explain why
protective sirtuin activity
is reduced in obesity,
a condition characterized
by oxidative stress
and inflammation.
A study of identical twin pairs
in which one, on average,
was obese and the other not,
found significantly
less sirtuin expression
in the obese twin,
despite having
the same genetics.
And randomize people
to a six-month trial
of 25 percent
calorie restriction,
and you can show a boost
in sirtuin expression
along with a decrease
in DNA damage.
Protein restriction
may have a similar effect,
since men and women
with higher protein intake
tend to have lower levels
of NAD+ in their blood,
thought to be due
to the oxidative stress
induced by protein
breakdown byproducts.
If oxidation and inflammation
are responsible
for a drop in NAD+ levels,
then what about the antioxidant
and anti-inflammatory
phytonutrients
in healthy plant foods?
After screening
more than 14,000 compounds,
almost all flavonoids
were found to be effective
in a test for CD38 inhibition.
The two most effective
were cyanidin,
found in red cabbage
and blackberries,
and quercetagetin,
found in marigold flower tea.
Another study found
the three most potent compounds
were luteolin, kuromanin,
and luteolinidin.
Luteolin is found concentrated
in oregano, radicchio,
and chrysanthemum tea.
Kuromanin is found
in black berries, purple corn,
and hibiscus tea.
Corn tortillas are
surprisingly easy to make;
so why not choose blue
or purple masa
to make them even healthier?
Luteolinidin,
found to increase NAD+
in the hearts of rats,
can be found in red sorghum,
one of the components
of my prebiotic BROL mix,
when I can find it.
The flavonoid apigenin
is a well-established
CD38 inhibitor.
When given to mice,
apigenin boosts NAD+ levels
by about 50 percent,
which is what people would get
taking the maximum
tolerable daily dose of NR.
The best sources are parsley
and chamomile tea.
A wide range of flavonoids
found in green tea, turmeric,
and fruits and vegetables
have also been found
to prevent NAD+ depletion
in human cells in vitro
at levels found in the blood
after consumption.
How much do you have to eat,
though?
Proanthocyanidins have been
found to lower PARP-1
and CD38 expression in rats.
NAD+ and sirtuin activity
was significantly boosted
at the human equivalent dose
of about 280 milligrams a day.
How much is that?
That's the amount
of proanthocyanidins
found in a single apple.
You could also reach that dose
eating two plums,
a half cup of wild blueberries,
a little over a teaspoon
of cinnamon,
or a little over a tablespoon,
like four teaspoons,
of cocoa powder.
Quercetin is another suppressor
of PARP-1 and CD38
shown to increase
sirtuin activity in mice.
The concentration necessary
to lower PARP-1 in vitro
can be achieved by taking
a quercetin supplement,
but typical supplement
manufacturers'
recommended doses
are up to 100 times
the average daily
dietary intake.
Thankfully, food works too.
Researchers fried up
one and a half yellow onions
and raised
quercetin blood levels
to about 75 percent there.
And so, two onions might do it.
There's no long-term
safety data
on high-dose
flavonoid supplementation;
so, public health researchers
suggest
"caution should be exercised
in ingesting them
at levels above which
would be obtained
from a typical
vegetarian diet."
Visit nutritionfacts.org/audio to see
all of the podcast episodes
with descriptions that include
links to their associated videos.
Sources cited and other details are
available on each video's page.
Information about my books—
How Not to Die, How Not to Diet,
and How Not to Age—
is at nutritionfacts.org/books.
All proceeds from book
sales go to charity.
And sign up for our free newsletter
at nutritionfacts.org/subscribe
to stay updated on the latest
bite-sized videos and articles.
NutritionFacts.org is a
science-based non-profit,
and everything on
the website is free.
There are no ads, no corporate
sponsorships, no kickbacks.
Strictly non-commercial,
not selling anything.
I just put up as a public service,
as a labor of love,
as a tribute to my grandmother
whose own life was saved
with evidence-based nutrition.
Thanks for listening.